Guide to the Greet Kershaw Papers M1661
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Greet Kershaw papers
1953-2003
M1661
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
2.0 Linear feet (3 manuscript boxes, one map folder)
Greet Kershaw, an anthropologist from the University of California, Long Beach, lived in Kenya from 1955 to 1957 in order to study the reasons behind the Mau Mau movement, an anticolonial movement, and the effects on the local people and the world. Included in this collection are her field notes, her M.A. thesis and Ph.D. dissertation among various correspondences with editors, articles written by her and other notable anthropologists and her contributions to published works. This collection also has maps, charts and photographs which Kershaw used in her research.
Due to limited resources, minimal processing occurred to this collection. Scholars may find paperclips, staples, and other original bindings along with letters in their original envelopes. A date span was given whenever possible. Since no arrangement occurred inside each individual box, scholars should note that the completeness of the folder heading could be suspect.
Kershaw, Greet (Gretha)
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical/Historical note
Greet Kershaw was a professor of Anthropology at California State University, Long Beach, when she went to Kenya in 1955. She remained in Kenya until 1957, traveling between four villages, Thuita, Itara, Mbari ya Igi and Nginduri and studying the Mau Mau. Her husband John Kershaw, a historian, accompanied her and assisted in her research. She earned her Master’s in Anthropology at the University of Chicago in 1960. She went on to complete her Ph.D. in Anthropology in 1972 also at the University of Chicago. Kershaw’s field notes and research culminated in a book entitled Mau Mau From Below which was published in 1997. Kershaw spent years writing her book, revisiting her field sites and exploring the aftermath of a movement. She also was an advocate for applied anthropology because she believed that anthropologists could do valuable work outside of academia. Kershaw also studied and wrote articles about the Hmong diaspora in Long Beach in the 1970s and 1980s.
Kershaw died in 2008. One obiturary wrote, "On Jan. 30, Greet Kershaw, 85, passed away after a brief hospitalization. Born in Amsterdam and raised in the Netherlands, Greet spent her early adult years as a social worker, many of those in East Africa during the 1950s and 1960s, later becoming one of only a handful of ethnologists with detailed, painstakingly collected data about the lives of the Kikuyu people who were at the center of the Mau Mau movement. She earned a Ph.D. in anthropology from the University of Chicago and was professor of anthropology at CSULB from 1966 until retiring in the late 1980s." [source: Inside CSULB, Vol 60 No. 16: Sept 2, 2008, California State University, Long Beach]
Scope and Contents
Three boxes of materials contain photographs, maps, field notes, articles and correspondence of Greet Kershaw, an anthropologist from California State University, Long Beach, before, during and after her fieldwork in Kenya. Also included are notes on her research on Hmong refugees in Southern California, her M.A. thesis and Ph.D. dissertation and her correspondence with various editors.
Acquisition Information
This collection given by Dave Kershaw to Stanford University, Special Collections in 2008.
Anthropology.; East Africa--History; Hmong Americans; Kenya; Mau Mau; Women anthropologists
- Correspondence, 1961-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains correspondence between Kershaw and various editors and publishers, her dissertation committee and film makers creating a special on tribes and their first contact with the outside world.
- "Husband Correspondence", 1957-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Contains a correspondence relating to a misunderstanding that Greet Sluiter (madien name of Greet Kershaw) in 1957 had a polyamorous relationship with a member of the Kikuyu tribe during her stay in Kenya. This misinterpretation sheds light on the difference between kinship labels in Kenya and Europe.
- Correspondence, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Contains a series of emails between Jon Lonsdale and Greet Kershaw concerning Louis Leakey’s research on the Mau Mau uprising is included in this folder.
- Mau Mau articles (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Contains untitled and undated articles about the Mau Mau’s origins and culture. Also included is a graph of the literacy rates, Christians and landowning demographics of the tribe.
- Kershaw articles, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Contains notes on colloquium lectures about social change in Kikuyu tribe and decision making in the Kikuyu tribe.
- Articles (alternate careers for Anthropologists), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Contains Kershaw’s remarks on a conference held on April 25, 1981 at UCLA entitled “Alternate Careers for Anthropologists” in which Kershaw defended the idea that there are fulfilling jobs for anthropologists outside of academia. She also replies to one of her critics, Dr. Susan Kent.
- Articles: Hmong families, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Contains an article entitled “Hmong families in Long Beach 1978- 1982: Between Incorporation and Rejection written by Dr. Kershaw when she was at California State University Long Beach.
- Kershaw: articles, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Contains articles entitled “War and Peace”, a proposal for a possible Peace Studies certificate and “The Tyranny of Ideology: A Case Study”, California State University Long Beach’s Anthropology Department newsletter and an article named “Running Fast to Stand Still” which highlights the roles of women in the Kikuyu culture.
- Contribution to published works (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Contains “The Changing Roles of Men and Women in the Kikuyu Family by Socioeconomic Strata” and contributions to “Cultural source materials for population planning in East Africa”.
- Articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Contains articles entitled “The People against John Smith, Anthropologist”, “A Model for the Study of Development and Modernization in East Africa” and an introduction.
- Mau Mau field notes, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Contains interviews, notes from participant observation and reflections of Kershaw's fieldwork in Kenya.
- Mau Mau field notes, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Mau Mau field notes, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Mau Mau field notes, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Contains interviews, notes from participant observation and reflections of Kershaw's fieldwork in Kenya are all included in this folder.
- Mau Mau field notes, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Mau Mau: list of people accused of bribery (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Contains a list of individuals accused of giving and/or demanding bribery and their accusers.
- Pseudonym code (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Contains Kershaw’s key to pseudonyms she used in her research and writing.
- Kikuyu concepts of land and kin. MA thesis, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Contains copy 3 of Kershaw’s (at the time Sluiter’s) M.A. Thesis submitted to the University of Chicago in November, 1960.
- Kikuyu concepts of land and kin. MA thesis, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Contains an additional copy of Kershaw’s thesis.
- Kikuyu concepts of land and kin. MA thesis, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Contains drafts of Kershaw’s thesis divided into chapters.
- Survey regarding fieldwork, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Contains a correspondence. In 1971, Dr. A. Molnos reached out to Kershaw and asked for demographics and information on West African culture and people in order to create a source book for "...persons who are preparing training and information materials to motivate East African peoples towards the adoption of modern family planning practices." Kershaw responded by sending Molnos information on family dynamics and demographics, current methods of birth control among the Kikuyu people, maps of eastern Kenya and her methods of investigation during her fieldwork.
- The Land is the People: dissertation, pp. 1-49, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Contains Greet Kershaw’s dissertation pages 1 through 49.
- The Land is the People: dissertation, pp. 50-111, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Contains Greet Kershaw’s dissertation pages 50 through 111.
- The Land is the People: dissertation, chapter 3, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Contains Greet Kershaw’s dissertation pages 112 through 207.
- The Land is the People: dissertation, atlas and tables, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Contains charts of kinship maps, population and mortality rate charts and marriage patterns.
- Maps (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Contains the following maps: Komothai region, south eastern Kenya, topical map of eastern Africa which shows native caravan routes, a Population, Tsetse fly and rainfall map of East Africa, and the Kikuyu native land unit.
- Maps (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Contains the following maps: approximate areas of land acquired by Mbari Ya Igi, part of Komothai location showing villages, Rukera and Jacaranda estates soil map, Komothai location map, and a smaller Komothai location map.
- Photographs (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Contains photographs of landscape, children, and villagers. Also included is a village map, a Komothai map, and a Kiambu re-fly map.
- Bibliographies (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Contains two bibliographies. One is a bibliography of books and the other is a bibliography of newspaper articles, periodicals and government reports and documents.
- Southwestern Anthropology Association, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Contains two newsletters from the Southwestern Anthropology Association. The 1981 issue includes an article written by Kershaw entitled “A Breath of Fresh Air”.
- Mau Mau from below; fieldwork and experiences, 1955-1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Contains correspondence between Greet Kershaw and Rhoda E. Howard on the publication of Kershaw’s article “Mau Mau from Below: Fieldwork and Experience 1955- 1957 and 1962” in the Canadian Journal of African Studies. Also included is a copy of the article.
- Mau Mau from below: typescript (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Contains a copy of Mau Mau From Below article, notes and a call for papers announcement for the Canadian Association of African Studies Annual Meeting 1988.
- Buijtenhuijs, Rob. Essays on Mau Mau, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Contains publication entitled “Essays on Mau Mau: Contributions to Mau Mau Historiography” from the African Studies Centre in the Netherlands.
- F. D. Corfield report, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Contains a copy of Historical Survey of the Origins and Growth of Mau Mau and Kershaw's notes.
- Regarding the F. D. Corfield report (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Contains a summary of and reactions to the Corfield report.
- Leakey articles (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Contains “By the Evidence: Memoirs, 1932- 1951” by Louis Leakey.
- Lansdale articles (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Contains “The prayers of Waiyaki: Political Uses of the Kikuyu Past” article.
- John Middleton: "The Kikuyu and Kamba of Kenya", 1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Contains a copy of “The Kikuyu and Kamba of Kenya” by John Middleton, correspondence between Kershaw and Barbara Pym, the British novelist and assistant editor at the International African Institute about an article Kershaw wrote in 1964. Also included is Kershaw’s correspondence with John Middleton.
- Reading Lists (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Contains lists of historical fiction, British writers who write about other cultures, mystery authors, Mark Haddon books and information on various libraries.
- CD-rom; 5" floppy disk (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Contains CD-Rom labeled Kikuyu files and a 5” floppy disk labeled “Mau Mau from Below Appendices” from 1996.
- 6 floppy disks (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Contains floppy disks from 1996.
- USB drive: "Mau Mau" (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Contains maps, summaries, codes and information about the Mau Mau movement.
- Cassette tape: "Henk" (26-3-93), 1993 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Contains one cassette labeled Henk March 26, 1993.